Because what you call you, your
perspective, your your um discernment,
your recognition is based on the thing
already being there. It's not the other
way around. So it's not like the the you
observer that's here watching it and
then it goes away. The observer is there
because of the presence of the mental
states. Which means if that mental state
goes away, that observer
like it just it doesn't apply anymore.
Maybe we could um
[Music] I don't know like explore like what's
I don't know like explore like what's
the
like I heard that quite a number of time
like you know like oh I have a lot of
anger but I don't have any lust or I
have a lot of kind of restlessness but I
don't have any doubt or things like that
and um something that I've in
contemplating is to see that try to to
see that the relationship between the
different hindrances and it's not about
like the specificity about one or the
other but it's more about like how
I choose to act and how that
um kind of open the door but like to all
of it and try to kind of see what's the
common ground of all of them.
So what what is the common ground? Yeah,
that's the Yeah. So we can we can
discuss that. So what is the what is the
common ground
in terms of how you experience it? Like
common ground between experiencing one
hindrance, experiencing anger,
experiencing anxiety.
Well, perhaps we should start out by
saying that as soon as you don't act
out, can we speak of the hindrance?
Yes. But the thing is uh
you don't see the full extent of acting
out initially. So practically speaking
your mind is pressuring you to do
something. Mhm. Um and and you are not
peaceful like it's it's quite obvious.
Um so to that and your perspective also
is constricted which is the main like
you don't see things clearly. That's the
main aspect of the hindrance. Like you
may not be acting out of the hindrance,
but um you can't tell apart left and
right basically. Mhm. You know that
you're not like making it worse by
acting, but
your mind is basically
sorting in doubt or whatever. Uhhuh. So
and and and now the question is what is
it that all the five indices have in
common? Yeah. Because then you would
realize that you can't actually have
only doubt and no anger or only anger
and no doubt only sensuality and no ill
will or something. Yeah.
So practically just recall one time when
you were experiencing the most recent
time that you were experiencing a
hindrance. What was the
the thing that preceded the hindrance?
The particular
um
characteristics of that hindrance
that would have been in common to all
other times that you also experience.
Well, it does involve a loss of
perspective. Mhm. Right. So being
identified let's per say with a content
and not seeing a hindrance as a
hindrance that's when you're hindered.
And uh but is that loss of perspective
just a just because you forgot something
that you could have just remembered or
is that rooted in something deeper lack
of perspective? Well, yeah. Okay. I
guess you're taking something for
granted. It's not even like you're not
it's not necessarily there for you to
recollect. Mhm. Yeah. But uh if you of
course taking things for granted is a
byproduct of being hindered. But because
you like from that perspective of where
you are now hindered,
you can say, "Okay, I won't take things
for granted anymore." But you'll still
feel the weight of that hindrance and you
the weight of that hindrance and you
still won't really like you because you
you would say okay let me not take
things for granted you would recall the
same ideas that before used to be um the
insights that you had developed or
whatever but now because of the state
you're in it makes no difference. Yeah.
Cuz you're not seeing your
that you're not seeing Yeah. But is it
only that something that you're not
seeing or is it more than that? Well,
the the loss of the perspective
is due to a previous acting out.
Yeah. Uh but
uh so the previous acting out what is
the more most immediate result of it
before the loss of perspective before in
a structural sense let's say not not in
time. Mhm.
I feel sense.
How does it feel basically?
Well, that's what we all already said.
Your mind begins to pressure you, right?
towards engagement basically well which
is always with the content and if you go
along with that that is the same as
losing the perspective. Yeah. So it's
pressuring towards engagement. But the
thing is like
um
that's the point like we want to see
what is the common ground between all of
them and so you you might say okay
especially towards this particular
engagement and then you might think okay
if I just don't do that I'm not
engaging. No no but it is more general
it is like from that point of view any
engagement. Yeah. So that that's that's
that's what you want to see. If you if
you see that pressure as such
before it even becomes a specific a
specific engagement then you can that
you can see that that's that that's what
the common ground is cuz that's how you
would fail to actually deal with the
problem is like you you think in terms
of okay sensuality
and okay it's pressuring me towards
engagement there so as long as I don't
do I don't go there I'm not engaging.
Mhm. But you could do you could be doing
a million other things still out of
pressure and that means that the common
ground of the hindrances isn't being
maintained. So just you're just kind of
um
like you have five glasses of of of five
empty glasses and you're just kind of
emptying moving the contents from one to
the other but you're not actually
getting rid of the water. M so um that's
that's what you want to see. It's it's
the pressure
in that most general sense mind that is
pressured. Mhm. And um and it it's
something that everybody has
experienced. It's not like um
like just imagine even before you
started practicing or something um
occasions where you were just completely
doing whatever you wanted just I don't
know partying or um
careless conversation um unh wholesome
activities and then at the end of it
you find yourself doing things saying
things that afterwards you regret. But
at the time it didn't feel you you
didn't see any problem with it. Um and
then you might even have like shouted at some
you might even have like shouted at some
somebody said something very mean to
them and then you go and afterwards you
regain perspective. You say oh sorry for
what I did that was actually stupid. uh
but at the time you didn't see it and
that's the why because you were caught
up in that pressure in the moment and
that's the that's the the practical
uh way to understand how when to say a
mind that is um pressured by hindrances
doesn't see what's for its own benefit
doesn't see what's for the benefit of
others or for the benefit of both. It's
not in some kind of um
mystical sense like it doesn't see
reality as it really is or something.
No, it's it's it's the it's just oh this
thing that I'm doing is actually harmful
for me. It's that simple. And and it
extends to to
if you take the hindrance in the most
fundamental sense because craving as a
whole uh appropriation as a whole uh greed
uh appropriation as a whole uh greed
aversion and delusion as a whole are
things that you also do which are not in
your benefit which are not in the
benefit of others and not in the benefit
of both. So
by being pressured by hindrances you
wouldn't you because of being pressured
by hindrances you don't see yourself
um taking things as mine
um being you know involved with the
aggregates involved with the sense
spaces on that most um kind of
acute level and so that's why then you
can't it's it's not a matter of choice
to like oh just try to understand these
things by kind of figuring them out without
by kind of figuring them out without
first purifying my conduct because
that's what this is to say leads to the
five hindrances is misconduct by body
speech and mind and misconduct not in a
sense of like um some external
moralistic sense it's just anything
that's rooted in greed and delusion
anything that's going to make your mind
wild and and uh like you take a child or
thing and you just let it do whatever it
wants to do.
Every every little desire that comes up,
you allow it and and like then
afterwards try to explain to him that
doing his homework is good for him.
It's not going to work. So, um it's it's
you have to look at it that way. It's
it's not even like
that's the domain where logic or or kind
of uh reasoning has a very limited
impact. Like at best you could the the
reasoning could kind of remind you of
like okay I have to restrain myself and
stop feeding this so that eventually it
will calm down. But you have to actually
recognize well I created this now and
well I created this now and
first of all my first concern shouldn't
be like in the moment just push it away
as quickly as possible cuz that's again
still going to be acting out of
hindrances. Um it's it's now it's like
Um it's it's now it's like
I need to
stop making it worse and then basically
keep in mind that the perspective will
only really return when that pressure
dissipates if I don't act out of it for
long enough.
So um it's uh it's um that's what the
training is and it takes place on
different levels of subtlety. So, uh, of
course, what I mentioned before was like
a very coarse example where you would be
actually doing things
um with your body or saying things. Uh,
if you're keeping the precepts, it
wouldn't go that far. But still, there's
plenty of room for you to um basically
become careless and and do things that
um not seeing at that time.
See, because because that's the problem.
Like when you're not under a hindrance,
you don't see
you you don't have the foresight to see
where you're going to end up, where
you're going to end up
if you keep going that direction. Cuz
right now, it doesn't hurt that much.
The mind isn't to So you think, "Oh,
well, I I'll handle it. It'll be fine."
Yeah. It's just a little bit just just
for this moment, I'll just do it. I'll
just give in to this pressure. Yeah.
Because you might actually be capable of
handling it, but you don't see how you
are already in the background agitating
your mind and then at some point it
begins to bite you and then it's too
late. And also you can handle it right
now because the mind or or at least so
you think. But see if you were able to
handle it then why did you do it? If if
you were able to handle the pressure if
if you were actually a quantum and you
were not moved by it then why did you
give in?
And then you realize it's actually just
a kind of um
secondary you don't even see your mind
basically otherwise you would see oh
wait like there you wouldn't be able to
overlook that direct relationship of
like pretty much chaining yourself to
this wild beast and and then you know
who nobody's going to come to save you.
So it's it's um that's why what what
matters most is like yeah inevitably you
will get caught up you you won't maybe
sometimes not even recognize like oh I
was actually being careless there but if
you find yourself now with a pressuring
state of mind of doubt or aversion or
ill will um you don't want to just find
a cure for it in the moment which is
with Most people tend to think the
practice about just use method
techniques to put out the fire that I
created through my own behavior and then
I delight in like just having the
perfect fire extinguisher
not in not bringing the fire into being
in the first place. So what you actually
want to think about is like okay so I
ended up with this pressuring state of
mind of doubt uh whatever sad mind
depressed mind and
um
okay let's say it will obviously have to
go away at some point because these
things are impermanent unless you keep
feeding them somehow.
Um but then then you want to actually
question yourself, okay, but why did
this happen?
And 10 times out of 10, you will see there
10 times out of 10, you will see there
was a pattern there of things that you
were doing. It didn't happen by
accident. Mhm.
So can you um
when you when you are pressured by
hindrance, how do you know if you can
how do you know if you can
think about certain contexts and and
themes to reestablish perspective
or if that's
not the right direction to go at the
time? So you're already pressured by
your hindrance
because it's not a it's not um
black and white thing. It's Mhm. It
depends like trying to discern those
patterns like you just said in the midst
of being pressured by the mind. Is that
what you're saying? Well, uh yeah, but
what what pattern do you mean? Like I've
been pressured by this hindrance. It's
because of my past actions. What were
those past actions? Right. Do you mean
like that? Well, yeah, even that could
be helpful, but but not necessarily.
Yeah, exactly. So, that's what I mean.
How would you know
when Yeah. When's the right time?
Because you could also fall into a trap
of saying like, okay, so there's a
hindrance now. I must not do anything. I
just sit here and grind my teeth and
just wait for and not seeing that that
attitude right there could be rooted in
the same same pressure. Yeah.
Well, that's basically also the answer.
So you so you want to see that um so you
want to take into account your
intentions for establishing that context
again, right? So what would be the right
intention?
Well, the right part of the right
intention is to not immediately want to
get rid of the hinders now for example
because then you're quite liable to fall
into your will but at the same time you
also want to maintain some perspective
otherwise you fall into doubt so so this
is well that is basically part of the
training and you want to do it wrong uh
quite a few times but then also at some
point you'll you will basically see wait
this perspective is now established
again um and So that's but that this is
all mental work right we are already
assuming this is not about talking to
yourself or just oh shall I go for a
walk or not that's how it starts in the
beginning but at some point it just it
just becomes completely
um because they are fundamentally
mental. Yeah. Yeah. Um but the thing is
so uh
what is it that you would need to
recognize in order to do that work on the mental
in order to do that work on the mental
level without as you said trying to get
rid of the hindrance because often
to most people it could sound as you say
okay don't try to get rid of the
hindrance means like I just
let myself be carried by it and then you
had whatever sensual hindrances or um
ill will and to you it might sound like
uh
not trying to get rid of the hindrance
means like okay so I just let that
thinking continue and and and basically
just wallow in it. Yeah. But from this point
wallow in it. Yeah. But from this point
of view the thinking might already be
sort of a byproduct. Yeah. Yeah.
Exactly. But you you do need to
recognize something
in order to rightly not try to get rid
of the hindrance because basically
there's a difference between just
um sherking your responsibility and
saying okay well I'm not going to try to
get rid of the hindrance and rightly um
not trying to get rid of the hindrance
in a way that actually started it and
and eventually brings it to an end. So
what would be that recognition that's
required there?
Well, I think it's the recognition of
the extent of the pressure when you kind
of when like the line between the
pressure and me quote unquote is kind of
clear like regardless of whatever is coming,
like regardless of whatever is coming,
you you know like it cannot pass this
point. Mhm. Regardless of what's come
and if that is very clear then you can
recollect recollect things that are
already present like the body or
whatever. But if this line is not so
clear, it's kind of like a sort of gray
in between the white and the black, then
you find yourself in the gray and
whatever you are doing there, regardless
if like trying to recolct the body or
whatever, if this line is not
established first, then you're just
spinning. You just Yeah. Like so I think
that the thing is that to recognize this
line first. Yeah. So you have to
recognize first you have to come to the point
first you have to come to the point
where you realize
nothing will nothing bad will actually
happen here. Mhm. Unless I do
intentionally give into this pressure.
Mhm. You have that's how you would
practically recognize like um that you
can endure it infinitely quote unquote.
It's like that has to be based on the
recognition like you said of that line such that
like you said of that line such that
even if it stays there forever
at no point will I actually do something
unh wholesome in account of it. Mhm. Um
so of course the precepts has to be have
to be established but even on the mental
level uh there is that work to to discerning
uh there is that work to to discerning
at which point
having the mental pressure of let's say
sensuality or ill will at what point
that becomes you thinking out of
sensuality and it will which the Buddha
said you never you should never do he
said like and and that's a confusion
that that often
um like When we talk about oh we have to
endure the sensuality the mental state
of sensuality or the mental state of of
ill will uh then people would quote the
sut saying where the Buddha says um oh
but as soon as a as a thought of
sensuality or a thought of ill will or a
thought of cruelty arises you should
obliterate it eradicate it and bring it
to an end. But those are two completely
different things. It's because the
thoughts are things that you do. It's
kind of your choice to to attend to
these mental images basically and the um
pressure the actual pressure of of
whatever hindrance it is that's
something that's even if you wanted to
you at best you could look away from it
it's going to be there anyway. Mhm. Uh
and so that's the crucial distinction.
You need to clearly discern. Okay, this
is the mind of whatever hindrance. This
is the mind of doubt. And this is the
line where
uh leaving it becomes
actually acting out of doubt mentally.
Mhm. And then you can um restrain those
thoughts of doubt. Yeah. Which is then
the right endurance of the hindrance of
doubt. Yeah. And practically speaking,
that that's really all you would need to
do because it's it's it's uh it's fueled
as a Buddha said. It's like a like a
like a fire. The only reason it keeps
going is because you have been throwing
sticks and and whatever cow dung or or
Mhm. things that are suitable for that
fire to keep to keep going. And but most
of the time, Brady, you don't recognize
yourself doing that, which is a problem.
But um once you recognize it, you see,
okay, well, you you even if it were to
last however long, you wouldn't feel
that burden of being like lost and and
cuz that's already a regaining of
perspective. Mhm. Just seeing like,
okay, so it it doesn't really matter if
it stays as long as I don't get involved
with it and make it worse. And then
That's it. Like just just stay there. If
it helps you to recollect the body or
recollect feelings or whichever other
thing you would do it now
maintaining perspective without line you
wouldn't do it like with the same
impetus of like I'm going to do this so
that it so I can push it away quicker or
something out of impatience which is
still within the indices
and then oh when is it going to go away
if that question arises is you realize
well I I shouldn't go in that direction
because that's again going to like why
would I worry about that unless I
started to overlook the fact that I'm
not actually there's there's nothing unh
wholesome going to happen here unless I
get involved. Yeah. There will be no
reason to worry about how long it's
going to last. Yeah. Which is again if
you give into that it's become it's
going to become either doubt or
restlessness for example. Yeah. and and
and you will realize that question
cannot be answered
like like there is fact like it's a it's
a the question is based on the wrong
premise because you can't watch your
experience from the outside and see the
one hindrance coming in and then going
away and then I no it's like you find
yourself because what you call you your
perspective your your
um discernment your recognition is based
on the thing already being there. It's
not the other way around. So it's not
like the the you observer that's here
watching it and then it goes away. The
observer is there because of the
presence of the mental states which
means if that mental state goes away
that observer
like it just it doesn't apply anymore.
Yeah.